德国飞机昨夜对英国
German aircraft
carried out a number of attacks
发动了多次袭击。
on Great Britain last night.
空袭持续了数小时，
The raids, which lasted
for several hours,
波及该国多个地区。
were scattered over many parts
of the country.
据报告敌机出现在
Enemy aircraft have been
reported over towns
南海岸城镇、英格兰西部、
on the south coast, the west of England,
中北部及西北部上空，
the north Midlands and the Northwest,
伦敦地区也发现敌机踪迹。
as well as over the London area.
来自德国的报道称
There are reports from Germany
我方轰炸机袭击了其工业目标
that our bombers attacked
industrial targets there
春天啊，伯顿先生 我本打算放弃它了。
Spring, Mr Burton I had been
thinking to give up on it.
是的 夫人 确实如此。
Yes, Ma Yes, indeed.
您今早要写作吗？
Will you be writing this morning?
当然 这正是我的计划。
Certainly, that is my plan.
哦 那我会保持轻声细语。
Oh Then I shall keep sotto voce.
您需要的东西都齐备了吗，伯顿先生？
Do you have everything
you need, Mr Burton?
是的 谢谢您，夫人。
Yes Yes, thank you, Ma.
好的
OK
慢点！慢点
Slowly! Slowly
？世间万物明亮美丽
? All things bright and beautiful
？众生无论大小
? All creatures great and small
？一切智慧奇妙
? All things wise and wonderful
早上好，伯顿先生。
Good morning, Mr Burton.
大家早上好
请坐
Good morning, everyone
Please sit down
我已收到你们最近的
I have the results
of your latest endeavours
多兰 优秀
Dolan Excellent
摩根 字迹潦草。
Morgan Handwriting.
别再让我重复提醒
除此之外 表现优异
Please don't make me tell you
again Otherwise, excellent
德里斯科尔。
Driscoll.
- 德里斯科尔先生呢？
- 他生病了，先生。
- Where is Mr Drisco"?
- He's sick, sir.
生病？啊 这就解释得通了。
Sick? We", that explains something.
呃 埃文斯？
Uh, Evans?
"elementary"里有几个E？
How many Es in "elementary"?
呃 三个，先生。
Uh, three, sir.
"三个E 请至少用上一个"
"Three, sir Please try and use a" of them.
其他方面还不错。
Otherwise, good.
其余人 及格 发下去吧。
The rest of you, fair Hand them out.
这是谁的？
Whose is this?
是我的，先生
That's mine, sir
詹金斯 我们或许不该
Jenkins, we may not
judge a book by its cover,
但缺了封面的书根本没法评判...
but we cannot judge a book
with no cover at a...
如果全国纸张短缺
If a national paper shortage
都不能让你们爱惜书本，
cannot persuade you to look after them,
那我只好亲自督促你们了。
I shall have to persuade you myself.
亨利五世 序章 "愿有火之缪斯"
Henry V, Prologue "O for a Muse of fire".
明天放学前 背诵全文。
End of school tomorrow, by heart.
但是先生 明天是尼斯队比赛。
But, sir, it's
the Neath game tomorrow.
他们让我打侧翼前锋
They made me openside
闭嘴
Shut up.
明天学校放假，记得
来这里找我。
End of school tomorrow, prompt
Find me here.
"愿有一团烈火的诗神。"
"O for a Muse of fire."
诗神是什么？
What is a muse?
- 有人知道吗？
- 诗人的红颜知己
- Anyone?
- A poet's bit of skirt
一年零三个月之后，
In a year and three months' time,
你们大多数人都会穿上军装。
most of you will be in uniform.
有些人可能被派往前线
面对杀戮，
Some of you may be asked
to go out and ki",
甚至直面死亡 为什么？
and may face death yourselves Why?
我这就告诉你们 你们将为
We", I shall tell you You will be fighting
善良、正义与美好而战，
for what is good and right and beautiful,
"而这些正是
那些事物的精髓。"
"and this is the essence
of a" those things.
想象这个场景。
Picture the scene.
阿金库尔战场 一边是
英格兰和威尔士联军。
Agincourt On one side,
the English and the Welsh.
亨利王和弗鲁爱林。
King Henry and Fluellen.
另一边则是
五倍于我军兵力的敌人。
And on the other,
a force five times our strength.
法军高举旗帜、策马挺矛。
The French with their banners
and horses and spears.
"愿上帝与我们并肩作战！"
"God's arm strike with us!"
"'敌众我寡，形势危急。'"
"'Tis a fearful odds."
但是等等。
But wait.
稍等。
Wait.
这时
Then
一支利箭破空而来！
a single arrow flies!
您确定吗，伯顿先生？
Are you quite sure, Mr Burton?
请别为了我特意过来。
Please don't come on my account.
既然剧院停演，妈妈，
In the absence of a theatre, Ma,
我宁愿待在这里
there's nowhere I would rather be
干得好，希斯。
Fine work, Hirth.
太精彩了，指挥官阁下。
Magnificent, Herr Kommandant.
现在，加拿大的帷幕升起
So, the curtain rises on Canada
意大利海军和商船队
Heavy new blows
在其本土海域、地中海中部
have fallen on the Italian
navy and merchant fleet
以及北非沿岸，
in their home waters,
再次遭受重创。
as well as in the central Mediterranean
这主要归功于我们的潜艇部队。
and off the coast of North Africa.
大部分功劳
属于我们的潜艇部队
Most of the credit
goes to our submarines
"我们称此地为阿金库尔战场，
"Then ca" we this the field of Agincourt
克里斯宾节当日之战"。
fought on the day of Crispin Crispianus".
既然您这么说，伯顿先生
If you say so, Mr Burton
我想和您的侧翼球员谈谈，大卫先生，
I'd like a word
with your openside, Mr David,
如果您不介意的话 就一会儿
if you don't mind Just for a moment
加油，小伙子们！
Come on, boys!
推，推，推 加把劲
Push, push, push Get it
"我们"上场了。
"We" played.
- 你怎么了？
- 伯顿先生
- What happened to you?
- Mr Burton
我三点半就在等您了。
I was expecting you at half past three.
我确实等了您，先生，真的 - 啊。
I did wait for you, sir, I did - Ah.
你是在暗示我迟到了？
Are you suggesting I was late?
呃，这是事实。
We", it's the truth.
"那你肯定"知道开场白了。
"Then you'" know the Prologue, of course.
"愿有一团烈火的诗神，直上
"O for a Muse of fire, that would ascend
最辉煌的创意天堂"。
the brightest heaven of invention".
"以王国为舞台，王子们粉墨登场
"A kingdom for a stage, princes to act
君王们凝视着
这盛大的场景"。
and monarchs to behold
the swelling scene".
"那时好战的哈里，
将如其本色
"Then should the warlike Harry,
like himself
披上战神的外衣，
身后紧随着"。
assume the port of Mars,
and at his heels".
很好——"如同猎犬般被拴着，
Fine - "Leash'd in like hounds,
饥荒、刀剑与烈火"。
should famine, sword and fire".
谢谢你，詹金斯
Thank you, Jenkins
我都能搞定，先生。
I can do it all, sir.
"不，不，那样就行"。
"No, no, that'" do.
是的，先生。
Yes, sir.
老实说，这惩罚不算什么。
It's not much of a punishment,
to be honest with you.
我他妈爱死这个了
I bloody loved it
我是泰巴赫未来的幽灵。
I am the ghost of Taibach future.
到我怀里来，小家伙。
Come into my arms, little one.
啊
Ah
- 你在这儿干嘛？
- 写作业。
- What are you doing here?
- Homework.
嗯 回头见
Hmm See you later
你又死哪儿去了？
Where the hell have you been again?
怎么？关你什么事？
Why? What's it to you?
学校今天下午三点半就放学了
School ended at half past three
this afternoon
如果你觉得我会把余生
If you think I'm going to spend
the rest of my life
都耗在那个该死的矿井里
slaving down that blasted hole
就为了让你——那又怎样？
so you can have - So what?
你要把我赶出去是吗？
You're going to throw me out, are you?
让我告诉你。
Let me tell you.
要是你父亲没那么酗酒的话。
If your father was less of a drunkard.
你敢 你他妈敢
Don't you dare Don't you bloody dare
里奇
Richie
作业？
Homework?
我给你带了热可可。
I brought you some cocoa.
谢谢。
Diolch.
别把他想得太坏，
里奇 他只是担心，毕竟...
Don't think too badly of him,
Richie He's worried, is a...
他胸口不舒服。
His chest.
这周他已经错过两个班次了。
That's two shifts
he's had to miss this week.
我"回庞蒂去
这样最好。
I'" go back to Ponty
That'd be the best thing.
"爸"会收留我 埃尔菲德也能
少操一张嘴的心
"Dad'" have me One less mouth
for Elfed to worry about
里奇，别犯傻。
Richie, don't be daft.
庞蒂那边现在一张床要睡两个人。
There's two to a bed in Ponty as it is.
你怎么去上学？
How would you get to school?
试着低调一点。
Just try to keep your head down a bit.
完成作业，打好你的橄榄球。
Do your homework, play your rugby.
总要闯出点名堂来
Just make something of yourself
啊。
Ah.
你的学生吗，伯顿先生？
One of yours, Mr Burton?
不，夫人，不是我的学生。
No, Ma, not one of mine.
BBC又给了我
一些制片工作。
The BBC have given me
some more production work.
哦。
Oh.
我们"，或许不是坏事，
就目前而言。
We", perhaps not a bad thing,
just at the moment.
我在想这是否对你有好处
I wonder if it wouldn't do you good
暂时把目光投向远方吧。
to look outward for a time.
你说得对，妈妈，你总是对的。
You are right, Ma, as you ever are.
毕竟现在是春天了。
It is spring, after all.
但我最想念的还是剧院。
Still it is the theatre that I miss.
嗯。
Hmm.
没有什么能替代它——没有。
There is nothing to replace it - No.
无论是广播还是电影都不行。
Not the wireless, not the cinema.
不行。
No.
我年轻时在基督教青年会经常参加戏剧演出。
We used to put on plays
when I was a girl at the YMCA.
噢，我太爱那个小舞台了。
Oh, I did love those It was
such a nice little stage.
妈，我在你这儿住了多久了？
Ma, how long
have I lodged here with you?
12年还是15年？
Twelve years, or 15?
你从没告诉过我你当过演员？
And you have never before
told me that you are an actress?
哦不，我...
Oh No, I
我演得肯定很糟糕
I'm quite sure I was terrible
快告诉我，你演过什么角色？
We", you must tell me, who did you play?
这个嘛...
Well, oh
我曾经演过朱丽叶。
Well, I did play Juliet once.
天啊！我居然错过了你的朱丽叶！
Ma! I curse the day
that I missed your Juliet!
哦，伯顿先生
Oh, Mr Burton
那匹马叫利布雷托，伙计。
Aye, anyway, Libretto,
the horse was called, man.
见鬼的是它居然赢了。
And damn me if he didn't bloody win.
你们可以随便评价赌博，小伙子们，
You can say what you like
about gambling, boys,
但我这辈子没见过比那更多的钱堆在一起。
but I haven't seen more money
in a single place to this day.
别提了 我父亲给全镇的人
Never mind a round My father
must have bought a drink
每人都买了一杯酒
for every man in Pontrhydyfen
所以到了打烊时分，
So, of course, come stop-tap,
就轮到我推着那个醉鬼爬坡回家...
it fell to me to wheel the
bugger back home up the hi...
那简直是场壮烈的攀登。
And an heroic climb it was,
I'm telling you.
等我们到家门口时，
By the time we reached his gate,
我喘得像台蒸汽机。
I was blowing like a winding engine.
"千万别忘了轮椅刹车，孩子们"
"Never forget the brakes
on a wheelchair, boys"
嗯？
Huh?
哦。
Oh.
我们的小里奇
Our Richie
珍妮，给这孩子来杯啤酒
Jeanie, get a pint for the boy
我也再来一杯
and I'll have another one myself
现在继续讲，小家伙。
We" now, bachan, bachan.
我就喜欢这种打断方式。
That's the kind of interruption I like.
我说到哪儿了？对了。
Where was I, then? Aye.
千万别忘了轮椅刹车。
Never forget the brakes on a wheelchair.
这可是个教训啊
There's a lesson for you now
我停下来喘口气的功夫，
I stopped for a minute to catch my breath.
转眼间，
The next thing I know,
老爷子就顺着山坡冲下去了，
the old man was careering down the hi",
又喊又叫
shouting and screaming
还拍打着轮椅扶手，
and beating the side of his wheelchair,
"加油，利布雷托 加油"
"Come on, Libretto Come on"
"冲啊。"
"Come on."
他那速度啊，我永远都忘不了。
The speed he was going I tell
you, I shall never forget.
"加油，利布雷托。"
"Come on, Libretto."
沿着车站路往下走，经过丹伊邦特，
Down Station Road, past Dan-Y-Bont,
我最后一次听到他喊："利布雷托"。
and I heard him one last time, "Libretto".
然后砰的一声。
And whack.
老托马斯撞上了高架渠的桥墩。
Old Thomas met the pillar
of the aqueduct.
当场毙命
Killed him stone dead
千真万确，
伙计们，千真万确！
Bloody true,
boys, bloody true!
哦，伯顿先生，开始了。
Oh Mr Burton It's on.
埃尔加
Elgar
乔治一直不喜欢他
我始终想不通为什么。
George never liked him
I could never understand it.
乔治错了，妈妈。
George was wrong, Ma.
就这么简单
Simple as that
客满无房
No room at the inn
还在我们这儿呢？
Still with us, is it?
我就知道你会来
I expected you would be
我有消息要告诉你，真的。
I've got some news for you, I have.
我给你找了份工作。
I found you a job.
埃尔菲德，你在说什么？
Elfed, what are you talking about?
周薪一英镑八先令
好差事 铁饭碗。
One pound eight a week
Good position One for life.
他还在上学 你知道他不能工作。
He's at school You know he can't work.
我像他这么大时，
已经工作三年了，
When I was his age, I'd been
working for three years,
每周六天。
six days a week.
但是，埃尔菲德
But, Elfed
不行 明年我还要考
学校毕业证书。
I can't Next year, I've got
the School Certificate.
我不能再让这个家继续拮据下去了。
I shan't have this family
falling short any longer.
他不能下矿井。
He's not going down the mine.
不 不行，绝对不行。
No No, he's not.
合作社有个职位空缺。
A job has come up at the Co-op.
服饰用品部
Haberdashery department
我军海军航空兵
在地中海成功袭击了
Our naval aircraft
made another successful attack
一支敌方运输船队。
on a convoy in the Mediterranean.
他们与皇家空军
轰炸了西西里和
And they and the RAF
have bombed many objectives
北非的多个战略目标。
in Sicily and North Africa.
一艘德军潜艇被击伤俘获
A U-boat has been damaged
and captured
海岸司令部飞机
与海军舰艇协同作战
by aircraft of the Coastal
Command and ships of the navy
早上好，伯顿先生。
Good morning, Mr Burton.
"夏日租约
期限"未免太短。"
"And summer's lease
hath a" too short a date."
有人知道吗？
Anyone?
- 第18号十四行诗，先生。
- 第18号十四行诗 谢谢，多兰。
- Sonnet 18, sir.
- Sonnet 18 Thank you, Dolan.
请坐。
Please sit down.
詹金斯先生去哪了？
Have we mislaid Mr Jenkins?
他已经离校了，先生。
Left he has, sir.
哦，是吗？没人通知我。
Oh, really? I was not informed.
我们"，只能试着适应没有他的日子了。
We", we shall have
to try to survive without him.
新学期已经开始
A new half-term is upon us
我们要开始研究哥特文学了。
and we must address ourselves
to the Gothic.
具体是奥特朗托城堡
In the shape of The Castle of Otranto.
闹鬼的走廊，
恐怖又难以解释的现象。
Haunted passageways,
horrid, inexplicable.
不对 不是那样。
No Not that way.
天哪，还要我示范多少次？
Dear me, how many times
do I have to show you?
抓住两个肩膀。
Take both shoulders.
现在提起衣领
把翻领抚平。
Now lift up the collar
and flatten the lapel.
翻领 你连翻领是什么都不知道吗？
The lapel Do you even know
what a lapel is?
为了。
For.
我的那份《广播时报》
送来了吗？
Has my copy of the Radio Times
been delivered?
刚到，伯顿先生——啊
Just this minute, Mr Burton - Ah
抱歉让您久等了 您知道的
I'm sorry for the wait You know how it is.
谢谢
Thank you
天哪，看看这盏灯！
Good Lord, look at this lamp!
快！把那些灯关掉！
所有人都出去！
Quick! Put those lights out!
Get out, all of you!
关上门！快！
Close the door! Quick!
这地方连狗都不该待
Place isn't fit for a dog to be in
宁愿在这儿也不愿在
隧道那头
Rather be here than on
the other side of that tunnel
我知道。
I know that.
关键是，五个人还是五十个人，
The point is, five men or 50 of us,
我告诉你们，我们正处在
爆炸的边缘
I tell you, we're on the edge
of an explosion
会把我们都炸上天！
that can blow us all to hell!
制作人：PH·伯顿。
Production was by PH Burton.
威尔士先生，总督察
Mr Wales, the chief inspector
早上好，伯顿先生——早。
Morning, Mr Burton - Morning.
"我们"
"We"
詹金斯 原来
Jenkins So
你一直在这儿。
this is where you've been.
是的，先生 有什么能帮您的？
Yes, sir Can I help you, sir?
哦对 这件，呃，夹克。
Oh, yes This, uh, jacket.
有条缝线需要处理下。
A seam needs some attention.
好的先生 当然，先生。
Yes, sir Of course, sir.
那么，你为什么
不去上学了？
So, why have you stopped
attending school?
我，呃。
I, um.
这个嘛 情况特殊，先生。
Well well, circumstances, sir.
家里，您明白的。
At home, see.
我理解。
I understand.
不得不说这太遗憾了，先生。
I must say, it's too bad, sir.
因为我一直很喜欢您的课，
特别是
Cos I always liked your lessons,
especially
我还在读您指定的
那些书
I'm still reading your books,
I am The ones you set.
哪本？
Which?
《我们》，莎士比亚的，先生。
We", Shakespeare, sir.
《我们》，至少听到这个我很欣慰。
We", I'm glad to hear that at least.
你要坚持阅读，詹金斯
没有比这更重要的事了。
You must keep reading, Jenkins
There's nothing more important.
谢谢您。
Thank you.
还有，祝你好运。
And, uh, good luck.
我，呃。
I, uh.
前几天晚上在广播里
听了您的剧。
I heard your play the other
night, on the wireless.
哦？
Oh?
非常精彩的作品
It was fine work, it was
《我们》，谢谢你，詹金斯。
We", thank you, Jenkins.
詹金斯。
Jenkins.
如果你对戏剧感兴趣，
If you're interested in the theatre,
我最近在基督教青年会
创办了个戏剧社团
I have recently started
a dramatic society at the YMCA
随时欢迎你加入。
where you'd be very welcome.
先生，您是在排戏吗？
像在学校那样？
You're putting on plays then,
sir, are you? Like at school?
是的。
Yes.
非常欢迎你来试试看。
You'd be very welcome Give it a try.
啊，妹妹你能想到这点
真是太好了。
Ah, yes, that is good, sister,
to think of that.
但是，呃，我不想卖掉它们。
But, I, uh, I don't want to sell them.
要知道，这是我母亲
临终时给我的。
You see, my mother gave
them to me on her deathbed.
詹金斯。
Jenkins.
啊，快进来快进来。
Ah, come in Come in.
加入我们吧
Join us
呃，能给詹金斯拿把椅子吗？
Uh, can we get Jenkins a chair?
欢迎
Welcome
你是来试镜的吗？
You auditioning then, are you?
我想试试看。
I thought I'd give it a go, see.
詹金斯，我们正在读
剧本《主教的烛台》的片段，
So, Jenkins, we're reading
sections of our play,
《主教的烛台》。
The Bishop's Candlesticks.
要不你直接来试试？
And, uh, we", why don't you
jump right in?
我们需要有人演囚犯这个角色。
We need someone to play our Convict.
囚犯的戏从第九页开始，
对吧，贝纳姆？
Um, Convict begins on page nine,
is it, Baynham?
是的，第九页最上面，先生。
Uh, yes, top of page nine, sir.
听着詹金斯，
这个囚犯是个逃犯。
Now, Jenkins,
the Convict is a fugitive.
而且他饿坏了。
And he's starving.
他带着一把刀
And he is armed with a knife
闯进了主教的家里。
as he comes into the Bishop's house.
明白，先生。
Yes, sir.
别紧张，尽管试试看。
Don't worry Just just give it a go.
好，时钟敲响12下
Right The clock strikes 12
贝内特，你来当钟声。
Bennett, you be our clock.
咚。
Dong.
- 再来点风声。
- 咚
- Let's have some wind.
- Dong
继续。
Of you go.
咚。
Dong.
咚 咚。
Dong Dong.
敢出声你就死定了！
If you call out, you are a dead man!
但是朋友，你看，我正在看书。
But, my friend, as you see, I am reading.
我为什么要喊人呢？
有什么能帮你的吗？
Why should I call out?
Can I help you in any way?
我要吃的 我快饿死了
I want food I'm starving
我已经三天没吃东西了。
I haven't eaten anything in three days.
快给我吃的 快点 该死的
Give me food quickly Quickly, curse you.
不错 第一次演就很像样
Good Very creditable First go.
我在想，
Um, I'm wondering.
如果他走投无路的话，呃
If he's desperate, uh
应该不想被人发现。
he doesn't want to be discovered.
或许我们可以试试，呃
Maybe we could try him, uh
更小声些？
Quieter?
小声点 好主意
Quieter Good idea
「敢出」声
你就死定了。
"If you ca" out,
you are a dead man.
好多了
Better
谢谢你，亲爱的。
Thank you, my lovely.
不过最好快点。
Best be quick about it, mind.
我还要赶着去看戏呢。
Going to the theatre, I am, see.
我儿子在那演话剧
My boy's in a drama there
演戏是吧？
Acting, is it?
我手下有上千个孩子
Children in a thousand, I got
祝你们好运
Break a leg, you two
这是表示祝福的话
It means good luck.
- 我们到了，妈
- 谢谢您，伯顿先生
- Here we are, Ma.
- Thank you, Mr Burton.
"那个..."演出结束后见
"And, uh, I'" see you after the show.
好的 祝你们一切顺利
Right And the very best of luck.
哦 我不该这么说的对吧？
Oh I'm not supposed to say that, am I?
我们只买了站票
We only paid for standing.
我爸今晚会来的 他答应过的
My father's coming tonight, he is.
别说了 吻我一下给我祝福吧
Don't say anything more Kiss
me and give me your blessing.
我去睡了
I'm going to bed
敢出声就要你的命！
If you call out,
you are a dead man!
- 台词？
- 我的朋友
- Line?
- My friend.
如你所见 我正在看书
My friend, as you see, I am reading.
我为什么要喊？
有什么能帮你的吗？
Why should I call out?
Can I help you in any way?
我要吃的 快饿死了
I want food I'm starving
我已经三天没吃东西了
I haven't eaten anything in three days.
快给我吃的 该死的
Give me food Quickly, curse you.
当然可以 孩子 你会有吃的
But, certainly,
my son, you shall have food
我去问姐姐要橱柜钥匙
I will ask my sister
for the keys of the cupboard.
坐下
Sit down.
我肚子里有头饿狼
I have a wolf inside me
在撕扯我的内脏
tearing at my entrails.
要把我撕碎
Tearing me apart
你演得太棒了 里奇 太棒了！
We thought you was wonderful,
Richie, wonderful!
还不算太糟对吧？
It weren't so bad, was it?
- 爸爸呢？
- 估计有事耽搁了
- Where's Daddy?
- Got held up, I expect.
好吧
Right.
詹金斯太太？
Mrs Jenkins?
詹姆斯太太 伯顿先生
Mrs James, Mr Burton.
这是我丈夫 埃尔菲德·詹姆斯
This is my husband, Mr Elfed James
我是里奇的姐姐
他现在和我们住
I'm Richie's sister
He lives with us, you see.
哦 - 您好
Oh - How do you do?
您好 您应该感到骄傲
How do you do? Well,
you should be very proud
理查德今晚表现非常出色
Richard excelled himself this evening
只是遗憾他不再上学了
I'm only sorry he's no longer
attending school.
他特别喜欢您的课 伯顿先生
He did love your lessons, Mr Burton.
整天挂在嘴边
Always on about them, he was.
如果有什么我能帮忙的
Well, if there's anything I can do
理查德是个聪明的孩子
Richard is an intelligent boy.
比在商店打工强多了
He could do a lot better
than working in that shop.
我明白现在大家日子都不好过
I-I-I do understand these
are hard times for everyone,
但或许可以让他重返校园
but it might be possible to have
him reinstated in school
我听到掌声了 太精彩了
I heard the applause Bloody marvelous
棒极了
Tremendous.
失陪了伯顿先生 再次感谢您
Please excuse me, Mr Burton
and thank you, again.
掌声雷动 震耳欲聋
Thunderous, it was A mighty roar
我在外面都听见了！
I could hear it out here!
加油。
Come on.
"现在大家日子都不好过"
"These are hard times
for everyone"
我明白他的意思。
I knew what he meant.
好像我没照顾支持过那孩子似的
Like I've not done and supported that boy
从他两岁起我就一直在帮他。
since he was two years old.
他愿意再给里奇一次机会。
He's willing to give Richie
another chance.
那小子机会多得都要从眼眶里溢出来了
The boy's had chances
up to his eyeballs, man
我是说，那我们呢？
I mean, what about us?
那些一直扶持他的人怎么办？
What about those who has to carry him?
他是个重要人物
He's an important man
管那种人叫男人？
Call that sort a man, do you?
埃尔菲德。
Elfed.
好吧 给我个帮他的正当理由。
All right Give me one good
reason why I should help him.
他什么时候帮过我？帮过你？
When has he ever helped me? Or you?
因为这个家从没有人完成过学业。
Cos no one in this family has
ever finished their education.
一个都没有，从来没有。
Not one of us, never.
埃尔菲德。
Elfed.
就再多一年 甚至不到，十个月。
It's one more year
Not even that, ten months.
到时候他就会被征召入伍，不管愿不愿意。
Then he' " be ca" ed up to
the forces, like it or not.
"你"再也不用资助他了。
"You'" never have to support him again.
那小子得自食其力。
The boy has to pay his way.
要是我自费去上学呢？
What if I paid my way
and went to school?
眼见为实
I'd believe that when I saw it
我能做到的，真的可以，不骗你。
I could do it, I could, honest.
我受够合作社了，明白吗？
I can't stand the Co-op no more, see? I
我什么都愿意做，我保证。
I'll do anything, I will I promise.
那就证明给我看。
Then prove it.
那就再见啦
Ta-ra then
干得好，你
Good work, you
明天见
See you tomorrow
我认为詹金斯有充分理由申请重新评估
I think Jenkins has
a strong case for reassessment
我相信他展现出相当的智力潜力。
I believe he shows considerable
intellectual promise.
复学许可非常罕见。
It's very unusual that
a reinstatement will be awarded.
但我们的职责是评估孩子潜力，
But it is our job
to assess a child's potential,
而非用过去评判他。
not judge him by his past.
没有旧报纸要卖给我们吧？
Haven't got any old papers
for us, have you?
让我看看。
Let me have a look, now.
找到了
Here we are
六十三份报纸，比上周多两份。
Sixty-three papers I got for
you, Edith Two up on last week.
那你想要多少钱？
How much do you want for them, then?
一先令？
Shilling?
詹金斯告诉我他的长期志向
Jenkins has told me that
it is his ambition, long held,
是成为一名教师。
to become a teacher himself.
回馈养育他的社区。
To give back to the community
that has supported him.
我相信詹金斯完成学业后
I believe that what Jenkins will gain
所获得的将千百倍回馈，
from completing his education
will be repaid many times over,
造福这座城镇世世代代。
to the benefit of this town
for generations to come.
请在外面稍候，我们要进行表决。
If you'd like to wait outside,
we can make a decision.
谢谢
Thank you
早上好，伯顿先生。
Morning, Mr Burton.
大家早上好。
Good morning, everyone.
还有，呃，欢迎回来，詹金斯。
And, uh, welcome back, Jenkins.
长官
Sir
我...我...我是值火警的詹金斯。
We", we", we"I Jenkins on fire watch.
好极了。
Jolly good.
你在读什么？
What are you reading?
詹姆斯·乔伊斯的作品，长官——哦，是吗？
James Joyce, it is, sir - Oh, yes?
啊。
Ah.
这可不是爱尔兰教育体系的最佳广告。
Not the best advertisement for
the Irish educational system.
我想找个机会
I wanted the chance to
好好感谢您，真的
多亏您让我重返校园。
well, thank you properly, I did
For getting me back into school.
"只要通过考试
这就是"我想要的感谢。
"Just pass your exams
That's a" the thanks I ask.
如果说灯火管制有什么好处，
If there is one thing to be said
for the blackout,
那就是天空变得格外清澈。
it's the clarity of the skies.
看，看到正在西沉的火星了吗？
Look See Mars setting?
- 那里有红色闪光？
- 是的。
- There's a flicker of red?
- Yeah.
你知道吗。
You know.
我曾经在莫哈韦沙漠的星空下度过一夜。
I once spent a night under
the stars in the Mojave Desert.
莫哈韦沙漠？在加利福尼亚？
The Mojave Desert? In California?
你去过洛杉矶吗？
Have you been to Los Angeles?
见过什么名人吗？
Did you meet anyone famous?
嗯，事实上确实见过 呃...
Well, as a matter of fact, I did Um.
埃迪·坎托
Eddie Cantor
多萝西·拉莫尔 —— 多萝西·拉莫尔？
Dorothy Lamour - Dorothy Lamour?
我们其实变得相当熟络
We actually became quite friendly
我当时在进行戏剧交流
为期六个月的学术休假。
I was on a theatrical exchange
Six months' sabbatical.
伯顿先生？
Mr Burton?
什么事，詹金斯？
Yes, Jenkins?
有件事
我想请教您。
There is something
I wanted to ask you.
或者说...告诉您，真的，我想。
Or-or you know, tell
you, really, I suppose.
- 哦，是吗？
- 我在考虑，您看
- Oh, yes?
- I was thinking, see
或许我
that I might
想当一名演员。
want to be an actor.
你想当演员？
You would like to be an actor?
我知道这不常见，
但我在想，您知道的，
I know it's not usual,
but I wondered if, you know,
您是否认为我能行。
if you thought that I could.
我能做到的，长官 我确信我能。
I could do it, sir I know I could.
- 如果您愿意帮助我。
- 如果我要帮助你的话（语法纠正）。
- If you was to help me.
- If I were to help you.
是的是的，长官 您明白吗？
Yes Yes, yes, sir You know?
如果...如果您能帮助我
If If you were to help me
我并非有意刻薄，詹金斯，但
I don't mean to be unkind, Jenkins, but
今天实在太漫长了。
it's been a long day.
"现在我只想"
凝望星空
"And a" I want for now
is to wonder at the stars
并且希望没人
朝我们扔燃烧弹
and for no one to drop
an incendiary on us
- 谢谢您，长官。
- 谢谢您，伯顿先生。
- Thank you, sir.
- Thank you, Mr Burton.
谢谢长官 - 谢谢长官。
Thank you, sir - Thank you, sir.
詹金斯，有空吗？
Jenkins, have you got a moment?
今天下午方便吗？
Are you free this afternoon?
可以安排，长官。
I can be, sir.
那好，詹金斯 跟我来。
Right then, Jenkins Follow me.
长官，我们接下来要去哪儿？
Where are we gonna go then, sir?
是"去"不是"去儿"
"Go" not "gor."
"去" 去 去 - 往那边
"Go" Go Go - Up there.
别往孤零零的洞里
Don't throw stones
乱扔石头，谁知道会砸到哪儿
into lonely holes without
knowing where they're going.
给我念念那块牌子
Read that sign for me.
"请随手关门"
"Please close the gate."
"门"不是"门儿"
"Gate" not "gairt."
门
Gate.
"请随手关门"
"Please close the gate."
注意听元音发音
Listen to the vowel sounds.
演员必须懂得如何展现台词的价值
An actor must know how
to extract their fu" value
"请随手关门"
"Please close the gate".
"Please close the gate."
现在
Now.
请随手关门
Please close the gate.
嗯？哦
Huh? Oh.
音高 发音 重音
Pitch Pronunciation Emphasis.
这些都是你必须掌握的技巧
These are the skills
you must learn to employ.
长官，咱们就在这儿聊吗？
Are we gonna talk by 'ere
then, sir, are we?
去 去
Going Go-ing.
还有 詹金斯 要说"这里"
And, please, Jenkins, the word is "here",
不是"这儿"
not "by 'ere".
"这儿"
- 缩短元音 "这里"
"H'yere"
- Shorten the vowel "Here".
这儿
H'yere.
送气音
Aspirate.
听说希瑟·霍德正在酒店里
Have you heard Heather Hodder
is here at the hotel
歇斯底里地发疯？这里
happily having hysterics? Here.
这里
Here.
回答你的问题 是的 我们就在这儿
And, in answer to your question,
yes, we are
我觉得史密斯夫人现在
I don't think Mrs Smith
would appreciate our company
应该不想见到我们
under the circumstances.
现在开始《亨利五世》
Now then Henry V.
先从开场白开始
Let us start with the Chorus speech,
这段你应该很熟悉了
with which, of course, you are familiar.
这段开场白就像是咒语
The Chorus is an incantation, as it were.
你的任务就是传达
Your task is simply
to deliver the meaning
这种特殊表达形式
of what is, after all,
伊丽莎白时期无韵诗的含义
an unusual form of speech,
Elizabethan blank verse.
开始吧
Let's hear it.
啊！愿有一支火神的诗笔
O for a Muse of fire,
引领我们直上九霄创新的天庭
that would ascend the brightest
heaven of invention.
停
Stop.
简直糟糕透顶
That is mostly dreadful.
重来 站稳 双脚抓地
Right Stand firm Plant your feet.
挺胸 抬头
Shoulders back Head erect.
好
Good.
再来一次
Let's give it another try.
能听清我说话吗？
Are you able to hear me?
是的。
Yes.
啊，愿我有一团烈火的诗神
O for a Muse of fire
能登上那最辉煌的天堂。
that would ascend the brightest
heaven of invention.
你能听到吗？
Are you able to hear that?
能。
Yes.
好，现在你来试试
Good Now you have a try
啊，愿我有一团烈火的诗神
能登上。
O for a Muse of fire
that would ascend.
停。
Stop.
我刚才在大喊大叫吗？
Was I shouting?
没有。
No.
音量，詹金斯，
是次要的。
Volume, Jenkins,
is of secondary importance.
清晰度，这才是你必须掌握的。
Distinctness, this is what you must learn.
现在，我要你尽可能大声地尖叫。
Now, I would like you to scream,
as loud as you can.
尖叫？
Scream?
尖叫
Scream
再来一次
And again
尖叫和喊叫一样，
Screaming, as with shouting,
就是尽可能从肺部排出更多空气，
is simply moving as much air
out of your lungs as you can,
并绷紧声带发出声音。
and straining your vocal cords
to make a sound.
而投射力，要充满整个剧场，
Projection, on the other hand,
filling a theatre,
这需要运用横膈膜的肌肉，
that is a matter of using
the muscle in your diaphragm,
这里，还有你的肺部，这里，
here, and your lungs, here,
这样你才能控制气流，保持清晰，
so that you can control
the flow of air, retain clarity,
并显著提高音量。
and make a significant
increase in volume.
因此，你的任务是区分
Your task, therefore, is to distinguish
这两者的不同。
between these two things.
所以，必要时就在这里待到天黑，
So, stay here until nightfall if necessary,
我们明早见。
and I will see you in the morning.
我想这是第一课。
First lesson, I believe.
你要把我一个人留在这儿吗？就这儿。
Are you leaving me h'yere? Here.
不停地尖叫
Scream and scream
直到找到不伤嗓子的方法
until you can find a way for it not to hurt
我知道这听起来很原始，
但会很有效。
I know it sounds primitive,
but it will be effective.
尖叫
Scream
再大声点
Louder
"所有东西"都在上面，是吗？
"Everything a" right up there, is it?
是的，谢谢。
Yes, thank you.
嘶...嘘...呼...
Sss Shh Fff.
嘛...
Mah
詹金斯，这位是我的房东史密斯太太。
Jenkins Mrs Smith, my landlady.
您好。
How do you do?
詹金斯想成为一名演员。
Jenkins feels that
he would like to be an actor.
哦，是这样吗？
Oh, is that a fact?
你的声音沙哑、失控
Your voice is raspy, uncontrolled
而且完全缺乏音域变化。
and completely lacking in range.
"事实上，我们可能"在浪费时间。
"Indeed, we may we" be wasting our time.
啊，愿我有一团烈火的诗神
O for a Muse of fire
能登上那最辉煌的天堂。
that would ascend the brightest
heaven of invention.
愿我的王国成为舞台，王子们来表演，
My kingdom for a stage, princes to act,
君主们来观赏这壮丽的场景
and monarchs to behold
the swelling scene
天呐，这嗓音。
Dear me, that voice.
这嗓音值得好好培养
他长得也很端正。
A voice you can work on
He has a good face.
端正的面容，还有猫一般的眼睛。
A good face, and eyes like a cat.
如果你想成为专业演员
If you want to be
a professional actor,
绝不能仅靠他人鼓励
it must be
not because of encouragement
而是要克服重重阻碍。
but in spite of discouragement.
你很有潜力。
You have promise.
但若缺乏训练
潜力永远只是潜力。
But without discipline,
promise will remain unfulfilled"ed.
有位老演员曾告诉我
没背完《诗篇》第一章六节经文
An old actor once told me that
nobody can play Shakespeare
就演不了莎士比亚
until he can recite all
six verses of the First Psalm
必须一口气背完。
in a single breath.
"不从恶人的计谋
不站罪人的道路
"Blessed is the man that walketh
not in the counsel
不坐亵慢人的座位
惟喜爱耶和华的律法
of the ungodly, nor standeth
in the way of sinners,
昼夜思想
nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful,
这人便为有福
but his delight is in the law of the Lord,
他要像一棵树
栽在溪水旁
and in His law
doth he meditate day and night,
按时候结果子
and he shall be like a tree
planted by the rivers of water,
叶子也不枯干
that bringeth forth his fruit in his season;
凡他所做的尽都顺利"
his leaf also shall not wither;
你之前知道这个吗？
and whatsoever he doeth
shall prosper ""
英文版的我没听过
Did you know that already?
那曾是火焰般的诗神啊
Not in English, I didn't
"雨点噼里啪啦落下
O for a Muse of fire that was.
滴滴答答淅淅沥沥"
"The rain comes pittering pattering down,
"农夫赶马进城去
plippetty, plippetty plop".
"嘚嘚嘚马蹄疾"
-理查德
"The farmer drives his horse to town,
"雨声淅沥马蹄急
"- clippetty, clippetty clop"
- Richard.
- "嘚嘚嘚马蹄疾"
-理查德！看在上帝份上！
"The rain comes pattering,
horse goes clattering,
你看不出老师在教什么吗？
- "clippetty, clippetty clop"
- Richard! For God sakes, boy!
你这种粗人根本不懂
Don't you see what this teacher is doing?
你就是个榆木脑袋
We", you wouldn't understand,
would you?
理查
You're an intellectual brute.
你
Richie.
这样说话
You
不只是在对我说
talking like that, you
你是在羞辱我们全家
you're not just talking to me, you know.
你姐姐、你父亲、你母亲
"You're talking it at a" of us.
所有养育你的人
Your sister, your father, your mother.
听着
Everybody you come from
我威尔士语是不太行
Look, I.
但我很清楚自己是谁
I'm not so good at the Welsh, I know that.
你的嗓音是天赐的礼物
But I know who I am.
你的嗓音
Now, your voice,
that's your birthright, it is.
噢，我感觉好奇怪
Your voice
你在香槟里加了什么？
Oh, I do feel so queer.
是啊 那些气泡
Did you put something funny
in the champagne?
花了我好几个小时
每个气泡都是亲手注入
Yes The bubbles
动作特别轻柔
It took me hours Every single
little bubble put in by hand,
不该给我点奖励吗？
rather gently.
[翻译结果缺失]
Don't you think I deserve
just a little reward for that?
哦，不
Oh, no
得不到那个吻
我就坐在这儿不走了
I'm not going to budge
from here until I get that kiss
而且我坐得可舒服了
and I'm sitting very comfortably
你赢了赌注？就你？
You won my bet? You?
狂妄的小子！明明是我赢了
Presumptuous insect! I won it.
你朝我扔拖鞋是什么意思？
What did you throw those
slippers at me for?
因为我想砸烂你的脸
Because I wanted to smash your face
我真想宰了你，你这个自私的畜生
I'd like to ki" you, you selfish brute.
这家伙紧张得很呢
The creature is nervous, after a".
哦？是吗？收起你的爪子，野猫
Ah Would you? Claws in, you cat.
你竟敢冲我发脾气？
How dare you show your temper to me?
我该怎么办？
What's to become of me?
头往后仰
Head back.
疼吗？
That hurt?
不疼
No.
不，一点都不疼
No, no, doesn't 'urt.
「疼」字要送气发音
"Hurt" Aspirate.
理查德，到底怎么回事？
What on earth is the matter, Richard?
演出搞砸了
The show went we".
是啊搞砸了，现在我要回
卡拉多克街了
Yeah, we", now I go back
to Caradoc Street.
那有什么问题吗？
There What is wrong with that?
那儿没人待见我
I'm not much wanted there.
哦，我可不这么认为
Oh, I hardly believe that.
你姐姐可疼你了
Your sister dotes on you.
问题是埃尔菲德
It's Elfed that's the problem.
他恨我 他在打压我
He hates me He's crushing me.
说真的，伯顿先生
我实在受不了了
Honestly, Mr Burton,
I can't stand it anymore
我都不知道该怎么办
I don't know what I'm going to do.
我父亲家里没我住的地方
There's no space in my father's house.
好了
There we are.
明晚应该能派上用场
That should be serviceable
for tomorrow night.
要是有空房
我就租一间
I'd rent a room,
if I could find one.
对了，史密斯太太
正好有间空房
We", of course,
Mrs Smith has a vacant room.
- 我可以搬去和你住！
- 嗯？
- I can move in with you!
- Hmm?
我很确定埃尔菲德
尤其是你姐姐
I'm quite sure Elfed
and especially your sister
- 不会同意的
- 能帮我问问她吗，伯顿先生？
- wouldn't want you to.
- Could you ask her, Mr Burton?
帮我问问？就问问她
For me? Could you? Just ask her.
天啊，不行
我不该提这事的
Dear me, no I
I shouldn't have mentioned it.
你看吧？
You see?
关键时刻
When push comes to shove
根本没人要我
nobody wants me.
我很遗憾，理查德
I'm sorry, Richard.
我必须承认
我确实有所顾虑
I cannot pretend that
I don't have my misgivings
我从没招过这个年纪的房客
I've never had a lodger of such an age,
而且他哪付得起
每周五先令的租金？
and how can he afford
five shillings a week?
但我...我还有其他顾虑
But, I-I-I do have other concerns.
你知道的，教年轻男孩是一回事
As you know, teaching a young
man here, that is one thing.
但让他住进家里？
But having him living in the house?
这肯定会
It's bound to fuel
惹人闲话
speculation.
妈，您真的不用为我担心
We", you do not need to worry
about me, Ma.
可我就是放心不下，伯顿先生
"Yes, but I do worry,
a" the same, Mr Burton.
况且这事可能只是纸上谈兵
Besides, this may be quite academic.
他姐姐和姐夫很可能不会同意
His sister and brother-in-law
may well not agree.
谢谢您，詹姆斯先生
Thank you, Mr James.
请讲
Please.
- 下午好 詹姆斯太太
- 您好 伯顿先生
- Good afternoon, Mrs James.
- He"o, Mr Burton.
- 需要帮您挂外套吗
- 外套
- Shall I take that for you?
- Coat.
如您所知 理查德向我提出
As you know,
Richard has asked me
想从这儿搬几条街的距离
if he might move
the few streets from here
住到我现在租住的史密斯夫人家
to Mrs Smith's house,
where I currently reside.
但是
But
我必须立刻表明立场
I should say at once, however,
我认为有诸多原因
I think there are a number of reasons
表明这可能不是个好主意
why this might not be a good idea.
可这明明是您的主意 孩子亲口告诉我的
But it was your idea, the boy did tell me.
确实 那个...
It is true, that, uh
我无意间提到有空房间的事
unthinkingly, I
I did mention a vacant room.
所以您不愿收留他？
So you won't take him on?
我绝非对理查德缺乏责任感
I do not wish to imply any lack
of commitment to Richard.
您知道 我为他投入了大量时间
As you know, I have
dedicated a lot of time to him.
帮他加入空军学员队
Enlisting him in the RAF Cadet Force,
辅导功课
and helping him with his schoolwork
还有表演技艺
and craft of acting.
事实上他在各方面
And, indeed, he has been made
remarkable progress
都取得了显著进步
in all these areas.
甚至可以考虑上大学
We might even consider university.
上大学？
University?
但搬离原生家庭...
But to move out of the family home is.
这可是重大决定
Well, it's a considerable step.
他够成熟吗？
Is he old enough?
他有这个责任心吗？
Is he responsible enough?
那您愿意承担他的房租？
So you would pay his rent?
经过深思熟虑 我愿意承担
After long consideration,
I would be prepared to meet.
那您就该收下他 伯顿先生
Then I think you should
take him on, Mr Burton.
请说
Please.
收下他吧
Take him on.
理查德在哪？
Where is Richard?
在楼上呢
Upstairs, he is.
或许我们该当面一起商量
Perhaps we should discuss this
together in the same room.
那我去叫他下来
"Well, I'" go fetch him, then.
詹姆斯太太
Mrs James
理查德首先是您儿子
其次才是您弟弟
Richard is your son much more
than he is your brother.
我明白你们感情有多深
I know how much you love each other.
请告诉我 您希望我怎么做？
Please, tell me, what is it
you want me to do?
若您肯收留他 伯顿先生
If you take him, Mr Burton,
这将是天赐的恩典
"it'" be the answer to my prayers
有人吗？
Hello?
八点整 理查德
妈妈最讨厌我们迟到
Eight o'clock, Richard
Ma likes us to be prompt.
知道了
A" right.
理查德，或许你可以在早餐后整理一下卧室。
Perhaps you could tidy your bedroom
早餐后，理查德。
after breakfast, Richard.
或许——或——许。
P'rhaps - Per-haps.
或——许。
Per-haps.
- 够了吗？
- 嗯。
- Enough?
- Hmm.
早上好——早，妈妈。
Good morning - Morning, Ma.
- 睡得怎么样？
- 像个无辜的孩子。
- How did you sleep?
- Like an innocent.
不，不，抱歉，理查德，
Right No, no, I'm sorry, Richie,
但这在这里真的行不通。
but that that really will not do here.
不。
Right No.
把边缘朝向你，明白吗？
Use the edge towards you Right?
不，不，不，不，不，不，不
No, no, no, no No, no, no
拿过来，拿到嘴边。
Bring it Bring it to your mouth.
明白吗？天哪。
Right? Dear me.
好吧！
Well!
对——这样好多了。
Right - That's better.
"无论你做什么，嘴里塞满东西时别说话"
"And whatever you do, don't
speak with your mouth fu"
哦，看在老天的份上
Oh, for goodness' sake
我就觉得闻到什么了！
I thought I could smell something!
可我只有这两双袜子，妈妈。
Well, I only have
the two pairs, Ma.
老实说，这袜子洞比袜子还多
Right Well, honestly,
there's more hole than sock
你母亲从没想过吗。
Did your mother never think.
"这是个"，好吧，妈妈。
"It's a" right, Ma.
我当时才两岁，对她一点印象都没有。
I was only two I don't remember
anything about her.
幸好有我和伯顿先生在这里。
We", it's a good job I'm here
Myself and Mr Burton.
好了，吃完早餐，
Right We", finish your breakfast,
然后把它们脱下来，
and then take them off,
"我会"看看能不能找双干净的。
"and I'" if I can't find some fresh ones.
- 那是什么？
- 嗯？
- What's that?
- Hmm?
哦，没什么
Oh Nothing
怎么了？
Yes?
你一个人住不会觉得孤单吗？
Do you never
get lonely, living on your own?
有修养的人永远不会孤单。
A cultured person is never lonely.
"时光之唇吮吸着源泉"
"The lips of time
leech to the fountain head".
"爱滴落又汇聚"
"Love drips and gathers,
但落下的鲜血将抚平她的创伤"
but the fallen blood shall calm her sores".
"而我无言告诉风天气如何"
"And I am dumb to tell a weather's wind
时间如何在星辰周围
滴答出天堂"
how time has ticked
a heaven round the stars".
太美了——不是吗？
That's wonderful - Isn't it, though?
天知道这是什么意思。
God knows what it means.
你在哪儿找到的？
Where'd you find it?
我有PH的图书馆，不是吗？
Well, I've got PH's library, don't I?
我甚至还有他的袜子
I even have his socks
你知道吗，理查德。
You know, Richie.
你和我预想的完全不一样。
You're not a bit like I thought you'd be.
怎么说？
How so?
"我以为你会更，呃"
"I thought you'd be more, we"
毛手毛脚
all hands
你懂我的意思。
You know what I mean.
而你从不对我那样。
And you never not with me.
是啊，我们说"我们"，
因为我是个绅士。
Yeah, we", that's because
I'm a gentleman.
其实你也想这么做，对吧？
You do want to though, don't you?
我当然他妈想啊。
Of course I bloody want to.
很好。
Good.
你怎么会觉得我不想呢？
Why on earth would you think I don't?
不知道，当我没说
I dunno It's nothing
理查德？
Richard?
我希望你重考
数学试卷。
I would like you to repeat
your mathematics paper.
我的数学？
My mathematics?
可是PH老师，您说过我考得不错。
But, PH, you said it was good.
是不错，但是呢
Good, yes, but, uh
不错还不够好
good is not good enough
可我想当演员，
不是教授啊
But I want to be
an actor, not a professor
理查德。
Richard.
要成为演员，你需要
进入特定的社交圈层，
To be an actor, you will need to
move in certain social spheres,
正好皇家空军有个新设立的
半年期奖学金项目，
and, as it happens, the RAF
have a new six-month scholarship
可以让几名学员
去牛津大学进修。
for several cadets
to study at Oxford University.
而我朋友西里尔·库克爵士
负责这个项目
And my friend, Sir Cyril Cooke,
is in charge
牛津？
Oxford?
对，牛津。
Oxford, yes.
但你的成绩必须非常优秀
所以...
But, uh your marks
will need to be excellent So.
从现在开始你有一小时
You have an hour from now
如果分数没有提高，
and if you do not better your mark,
我会再给你安排重考。
I will set you another.
好的，PH老师。
Yes, PH.
对了理查德？
Oh, and Richard?
如果你继续
在约谈时迟到，
If you continue to be late
for our appointments,
我可能不得不
重新考虑我们的约定。
I may be forced
to reconsider our arrangement.
明白我的意思吗？
Do I make myself clear?
抱歉。
Sorry.
我那个...
I, um.
呃...
Uh.
PH老师，我不知道
您还给剧院写剧本。
I didn't know you was writing
for the theatre, PH.
是的。
Yes.
不过如你所见
Although, as you can see
HM坦南特公司
并不满意。
not to the satisfaction
of HM Tennent Limited.
但您的作品
对BBC来说足够好了。
Well, your work's good enough
for the BBC.
BBC地方台而已。
A regional service of the BBC.
我本来有机会去伦敦工作...
I did have a job in London We...
至少收到过工作邀约。
The offer of a job, at least.
但后来战争爆发了。
But then the war broke out.
您是说，您其实
不想当老师？
You mean, you don't want
to be a teacher?
不，别误会。
No Don't misunderstand me.
我认为教书是崇高的职业
I believe teaching is a noble profession
只是没想到
I suppose I didn't think
会花大半辈子做这个。
I'd spend so much of my life doing it.
但劳工部认为
But the Ministry of Labour
以我的才能
considers my talents, such as they are,
更适合教书
而不是去广播大厦工作。
better suited to the classroom
than Broadcasting House.
所以就这样了。
And thus.
我与伦敦戏剧界渐行渐远。
I fell out of step with the London stage.
那你后来还写过其他剧本吗？
So, have you written other plays, then?
可能写得太多了。
Too many, perhaps.
所以即便屡遭挫折
So, writing must also be pursued
也必须坚持写作。
in spite of discouragement.
我想确实如此。
I suppose it must.
PH，没人比你更懂戏剧。
PH, no one understands the stage
like you.
这点我非常确定
I know that for certain
我是说你的导演工作。
I mean, your work as a director.
我总怀着惊叹欣赏。
I watch it in wonder I do.
要不是你在这儿
And if you hadn't been h'yere
在这儿。
Been here.
我们", 真难说。
We", I dunno.
可能永远都不会相识。
We never would have met.
我得给你看个东西。
I must show you something.
虽然只是些小角色，
Now, they are only minor roles,
但竞争会非常激烈。
and there will be fierce competition.
"埃姆林想要威尔士演员。"
"Emlyn wants Welsh actors."
"埃姆林·威廉姆斯先生正在寻找
"Mr Emlyn Williams is looking for
多名威尔士演员
several Welsh actors and actresses
参演其新剧中的小角色"。
for small parts in his new play".
"所需类型从年轻人到性格演员不等"
"Types wanted vary from young
people to character actors"
我可以转达我们的意向。
I could inform him of our interest.
是你的意向。
Of your interest.
埃姆林·威廉姆斯
Emlyn Williams
我确实和威廉姆斯有些交情。
I do know Williams a bit.
谢谢。
Thank you.
你该休息了。
You should get some sleep.
愿有烈火诗神
O for a Muse of fire
助我登临
that would ascend
灵思最璀璨的天庭。
the brightest heaven of invention.
以王国为舞台，王公当演员
A kingdom for a stage, princes to act
帝王列座观此恢弘场景。
and monarchs to behold
the swelling scene.
继而战神般的哈里王，本色登场，
Then, should the warlike Harry,
like himself,
尽显战神威仪，
assume the port of Mars,
身后饥馑、兵戈与烈焰如猎犬匍匐，
and at his heels, leashed in like hounds,
静候差遣
should famine, sword and fire
crouch for employment
西里尔，这孩子最近确实判若两人。
He really is a changed boy
these days, Cyril.
参加空训队，加入消防值班，
In the ATC, on the fire-watch rota,
成绩也突飞猛进。
and his marks have improved
beyond all recognition.
我一向尊重你的判断，PH
Well, you know I respect
your judgement, PH
自然会支持你。
I will support you, of course.
不过坦白说，我预见到些问题。
Although, to be candid,
I do foresee certain problems.
比如他的出身，是矿工之子吧？
His background, for instance
He's a miner's son, isn't he?
当然我对矿工子弟绝无偏见，
Not that I have anything against
miners' sons, of course,
但牛津剑桥向来不青睐这类生源。
but, um, they are hardly the
type that Oxbridge smiles on.
此外
And then
还有姓氏问题。
there is the matter of the surname.
这...什么意思？
How How do you mean?
孩子姓詹金斯，而你姓伯顿。
The boy's name is Jenkins
Yours is Burton.
他和你住在一起
He lives with you
这难免会引发一些疑问。
and it will inevitably lead to questions.
而且皇家空军奖学金竞争如此激烈。
And with competition for
the RAF scholarship so fierce.
总之，最好抓紧时间
这场战争不会自己打赢。
Anyhow, best get on
This war isn't winning itself.
是的是的，当然 谢谢您，西里尔爵士。
Yes Yes, of course Thank you, Sir Cyril.
听着，PH，我知道在这个时代
Look, PH, I know a man's name
shouldn't hold him back
一个人的名字不该成为阻碍
in this day and age, but
you know how these things work
水珠在滴落
The drops are dripping
那是迪克·詹金斯的儿子
That's Dic Jenkins's boy, that is
不会吧？
It's not, is it?
和那个老师住在一起
Living with that teacher
- 猜猜他图什么。
- 是啊
- Guess what he's after.
- Yeah
再来点茶吗，PH？
More tea, PH?
哦好的 谢谢你，理查德。
Oh Yes Thank you, Richard.
理查德。
Richard.
我们需要讨论你申请
We need to discuss your
application for a scholarship
牛津大学奖学金的事。
to Oxford University.
好的。
Right.
你知道，这是个难得的机会。
As you know,
this is an enormous opportunity.
而且幸运的是，
And, thankfully,
西里尔爵士已同意支持这次申请。
Sir Cyril has agreed
to support the application.
太好了。
Lovely.
但有个条件。
But there is a a caveat.
他认为我以关心你的老师身份推荐你
He believes that my putting you forward
会引发关于你居住安排的尴尬问题。
as a concerned teacher
我明白了。
will raise awkward questions
about your living arrangements.
要让我的推荐
I see.
毫无异议地被接受，
For me to put you forward,
就需要我
and for that to be accepted
without question,
对你承担法律责任。
would require me to
什么意思，法律责任？
to take legal responsibility for you.
收养我？
What do you mean, legal?
把这看作达到目的的手段，一种形式，但
Adopt me?
不可避免地，这需要你
Think of this as a means
to an end, a formality, but
改我的名字？
inevitably, this would require you to.
行。
Change my name?
改吧。
Fine.
好的。
Change it.
呃，要做到这点，
Right.
我们需要你现任法定监护人的许可。
Um, in order to do that,
是谁？是西斯吗？
we would need the permission
of your current legal guardian.
不，恐怕不是
Who's that? Is it Cis?
这该死的到底是谁？
No I'm afraid not
这能让我上大学。
Who the bloody hell is this?
甚至可能是牛津。
It would a"ow me to go to university.
我需要你签字。
Perhaps even to Oxford.
"婴儿理查德·沃尔特·詹金斯，
I need you to sign it.
自即日起，
"The infant, Richard Walter Jenkins,
完全放弃并终止使用父母的姓氏，
shall, from the date hereof,
[翻译结果缺失]
absolutely renounce and abandon
the surname of the parent,
理查德·沃尔特·詹金斯
Richard Walter Jenkins
并将采用养父的姓氏
and shall bear the surname
of the adopter,
菲利普·亨利·伯顿
Philip Henry Burton
对外公开身份
and shall be held out to the world
并在各方面都视同
and in all respects treated
"如同他确实是收养人的亲生子女"
"as if he were, in fact,
the child of the adopter"
听着，小子
We", boy
你得知道这件事
you need to know.
这可不是白给的
This won't come for nothing
五十英镑？
Fifty pounds?
你想要什么面额的钞票？
And how would you like the notes?
呃，五英镑面额的就行
Uh, five-pound notes will be fine
他是苏格兰人吧？
He's from Scotland, isn't he?
待在这儿
Stay here.
PH - 这是最好的安排
PH - It's for the best
嘿
Hey.
还要再来点吗？
Do you want any more?
我还有十英镑
I've got another ten
听着，小伙子
We", lad.
看来那些男孩说得没错
Looks like the boys are right.
他们说你变成娘娘腔了
They said you'd turned into a poofter.
嗯
Hmm
我们回家路上把这个寄出去
We'll pop this in the post
on the way home.
我...我想我需要散散步
I, uh I think I need to take a walk.
当然
Of course.
晚餐时见
I-I'll meet you for dinner.
或许我们可以开瓶酒
Maybe we'll open a bottle
里奇？
Richie?
啊，你在这儿
Ah, there you are
你以为灌醉我就能得逞？
Thought you'd get me drunk, did you?
当然不是
Of course not.
我只是想...庆祝一下
I thought, uh, well,
we have things to celebrate.
难道不值得庆祝吗？至少纪念一下
Do we not? Or mark, at any rate.
你的考试成绩，还有...
Your exam results, and.
我们共同取得的成就
We ", a" we have achieved together
里奇 你会吵醒妈妈的
Richie You'll wake up Ma.
我这就关门
"- I'" shut this door
伯顿先生？
Mr Burton?
你真当我是傻子吗？
Do you really think I'm that stupid?
你以为我不知道你在打什么主意？
Do you think I don't know
what you're up to?
什么？你在说什么？
What What are you talking about?
你心知肚明
You know very we"
what I'm talking about.
理查德 - 好老PH啊，是吧？
Richard - Good old PH, eh?
他是怎么...
How he, um
给我穿衣服
clothed me.
给我饭吃
He fed me.
纯粹出于好心
A" out of the goodness of his heart
理查德，我给你泡杯茶吧
Richard, let me make you a cup of tea.
这他妈是全塔尔伯特港公开的秘密
It's the worst-kept secret
in fucking Port Talbot.
理查德
Richard.
今天真是漫长的一天，发生了不少事。
It's been an eventful day A long day.
我想你也需要休息了。
And you I'm sure you need some sleep.
你以为我不知道你在打什么主意吗？
Do you think I don't know
what it is that you want?
理查德
Richard
我为你付出了一切，满足了你所有的要求，
I have done everything for you,
everything that you requested,
却从未索取过任何回报。
and I have asked for nothing in return.
除了希望看到你在演艺事业上有所成就。
Nothing, except to
to see you flourish as an actor.
是的，或许还期待一点感激之情，但老天爷啊。
Yes, perhaps a little gratitude,
but good God.
再过几周，
In a matter of weeks,
你就要参加达芙妮·赖的试镜了
you will be auditioning for Daphne Rye
达芙妮·赖。
Daphne Rye.
她可能是全国最具影响力的选角导演。
Perhaps the most influential
casting director in the country.
而且她会特别关注你的表现。
And she will be paying you
particular attention.
你觉得这些机会都是凭空而来的吗？
Do you suppose these things
happen by chance?
还是说...你觉得你有什么特别之处？是这样吗？
Or-or-or are you in some way
special? Is that it?
理查德？
Richard?
回答我，是不是？
Well, is it?
里奇，你到底在干什么？
Richie What on earth are you doing?
快下来，我们需要谈谈
Come down, will you?
I need to talk to you
妈妈，昨晚打扰到您我很抱歉
I am sorry if we disturbed
you last night, Ma
不，你们没有打扰我。
Well, no you didn't disturb me.
我给你泡杯茶吧。
Let me make you some tea.
恐怕我们得给您找新房客了。
I am afraid we may have
to find you a new tenant.
伯顿先生。
Mr Burton.
我不想说我早就担心会这样，
I don't want to say that
I was afraid this would happen,
因为...我明白。
because - I know.
我不想说里奇的坏话，
I don't want to speak ill of Richie,
尽管他的行为如此恶劣
however terribly he's behaved
因为我真的很喜欢这个孩子。
because I've become so fond of the boy.
还记得基督教青年会那场首演吗？
Do you remember
that first play at the YMCA?
我们...
We...
他从一开始就是这样对我的。
That's how he's been to me,
right from the start.
可以说是胆怯又戒备。
Scared and hunted, I suppose you'd say.
就算我们给予他全世界的善意，
We could have given him
all the kindness in the world,
也永远改变不了这一点。
and nothing was ever
going to change that, ever.
但他居然这样回报我？
"But to throw it a" back at me?
我知道。
I know.
但还有谁呢，伯顿先生？
But who else, Mr Burton?
您应该明白。
You must know that.
他还在乎过谁呢？
Who else does he care about so much?
我们需要找的是个男孩
I'm afraid it is a boy
we are looking for
但她可以女扮男装啊，赖小姐，不是吗？
But she could pass
for a boy, Miss Rye, isn't it?
毕竟现在是在打仗期间。
There is a war on, after all.
是的，巴伦太太，但我们需要的是个男孩。
Yes, Mrs Barron, but it is a boy
we are looking for.
请坐到左边去。
Please, take a seat to the left.
唐纳德·布朗。
Donald Brown.
唐纳德·布朗？
Donald Brown?
不在？好吧。
No? Very we.
理查德·伯顿
Richard Burton
站直了
Stand up straight
别忘了保持微笑。
Don't forget to smile.
啊，没错。你是菲利普·伯顿的徒弟。
Ah, yes You're Philip Burton's boy.
是的，莱伊小姐。
Yes, Miss Rye.
我，呃...
I, um.
您发来的台词...我都背下来了。
I've, uh, I've memorised
the lines you sent.
那就开始吧。
Carry on, then.
干草还没收完
What do I want with stories
我哪有心思听故事？
when I got the hay to get in?
自从被种马摔伤卧床后
I 'aven't read a story,
not since I was in bed
我就再没读过故事了。
from the stallion throwin' me.
我得想些别的事。
I got to think about other things.
比如姑娘们。
Like girls.
还有明天的天气会怎样
And what is the sky like for tomorrow
以及一品脱啤酒的滋味。
and the taste of a pint.
当然还有姑娘们。
And girls.
谢谢。能看看你的侧脸吗？
Thank you May I see your profile?
想看另一侧也行，随你便。
You can see the other
side too, if you like.
两边差别很大吗？
Is it particularly different?
你来说说看。
You tell me.
天呐，你可真够大胆的，不是吗？
Dear me, you are a bold one, aren't you?
你根本想象不到。
You cannot imagine.
你的时间安排？你现在在皇家空军？
And your availability? You're in the RAF?
我看到菲利普提到奖学金的事。
I see Philip mentions a scholarship.
是的。四月份皇家空军会送我去牛津，
Yes In April, the RAF
are sending me to Oxford.
埃克塞特学院。
Exeter College.
在那之前，我的时间都归您安排。
Till then, my time is yours.
请留下来坐会儿吧。
Stay and take a seat, if you would.
大卫·塞西尔。
David Cecil.
- 大卫 很高兴又见面了
- 我也很高兴见到你
- David Lovely to see you again.
- Nice to see you too.
剧本收到了吗？
Did you receive the play?
那么，可爱的浪子啊，等你当上国王后
Marry, then sweet wag,
when thou art king,
可别让我们这些夜的随从
let not us that are squires
of the night's body
被称作白昼之美的窃贼
be called thieves of the day's beauty.
你说得对
Thou sayest well,
因为我们这些月亮的子民
for the fortune of us
that are the moon's men
命运就像潮汐般涨落
doth ebb and flow like the sea
正如大海受月亮牵引
being governed, as the sea is,
by the moon.
不，理查德 这些都是喜剧场景
No, Richard These are comic scenes.
就不能演得轻松些吗？
Can't you make it a little lighter?
哈尔是个逃学者，是个追求享乐
Hal is a truant,
a boy who seeks enjoyment
而非体面的少年
rather than respectability.
就像你总提醒我的那样
As you keep telling me.
那么，你到底哪里没理解？
So, what exactly are you failing to grasp?
你自己不也在追求享乐吗？
You yourself seek enjoyment,
do you not?
据我所见简直是日夜不停
Day and bloody night, as far as I can tell.
事实上无处不在，除了这里这个关键场合
Everywhere, in fact,
except here, where it matters.
五点了 - 谢谢
It's five o'clock - Thank you
理查
Rich.
这是最后一次机会
That is your last.
明白吗？你必须振作起来
Do you understand? You need
to pull yourself together
我完好无损
I am perfectly intact
你喝得烂醉如泥
You are arseholed.
理查德，再说一次
换其他演员早就妥协了
Again, Richard,
any other actor would give.
演员！
Actors!
我他妈恨透演员了
I fucking hate actors.
还有他们那些该死的化妆品
Them and their their make-up.
你说说看
什么样的男人会涂脂抹粉？
You know, what kind of man
wears make-up? I ask you that.
容我再次提醒您
Give me leave to tell you
once again that at my birth
我出生时天象异变
the front of heaven
was full of fiery shapes.
他来了
Here he is.
英格兰的格伦道尔
The English Glendower.
看啊 威尔士亲王哈尔
And behold, the Welsh Prince Hall
简直是奇耻大辱
The indignity of it
梅尔
Mel
给那个醉醺醺的矿工儿子当替补
Understudy to the drunken son
of a drunken bloody miner.
什么？
What?
开个玩笑而已 理查
It was just a joke, Rich.
不过咱们实话实说
Although, let's face it.
说什么实话？
Let's face what?
理查！
Rich!
天啊 你把我鼻子打断了！
Jesus Christ You broke my nose!
- 只是擦伤
- 理查德 跟我来
- It's just a scratch.
- Richard, come with me.
终于 我还以为你永远不会屈服
At last I thought
you would never capitulate.
别弄脏我的衬衫和领带
Make sure it doesn't go on my shirt or tie.
你他妈到底有什么毛病？
Just what the hell is wrong with you?
离首演只剩四天了
Four bloody days until opening night
我跟托尼说过
这个角色非你莫属
I told Tony you were
the only actor for the part.
我向他保证会搞定你
And I promised him I would sort you out.
你？
You?
搞定我？
Sort me out?
没人能搞定我
Nobody can sort me out.
理查德 我的忍耐是有限度的
Richard, I do in fact have a limit
399号 史密斯夫人
399, Mrs Smith speaking.
哦 小理查
Oh, Rich Richie
理查 怎么了？
Richie, Richie, what's the matter?
不 理查 现在太晚了
Uh No, Richie, no
Richie, no, it's terribly late.
都凌晨一点了 真的不行
It's gone one o'clock I couldn't possibly.
别这样 嘘——
No, Richie Shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh.
妈
Ma.
我不确定这是好主意
"I'm not at a" sure this is a good idea
我觉得该给他打个电话
I think I should telephone him.
伯顿先生 他现在肯定还在昏睡
Mr Burton, there's not a cat's
chance that he's awake yet.
昨晚他醉得不省人事
He was very much the worse for wear.
但他明确表示急需见你
But he made it clear
that he needs you, urgently.
- 可就这样离开...
- 我会去学校
- But just to leave like.
- I shall call by the school
说明一下情况
and explain the situation.
伯顿先生 理查现在归你管
Now, Mr Burton,
Richie is your responsibility.
我知道你们上次闹得不愉快
Now, I know that you didn't
part on the best terms,
但你必须负起这个责任
but the fact remains, this is your duty.
如果他需要你，你就必须去
If he needs you, then you must go
伯顿先生。
Mr Burton.
理查德。
Richard.
啊
Ah
你不记得了，呃。
You don't recall, uh.
你昨晚和史密斯夫人
通过电话。
You spoke to Mrs Smith
on the telephone last night.
天啊。
Dear God.
我当时一定是喝醉了
I must have been drunk
那么"妈"还好吗？
Is Ma we", then?
她身体非常健康。
She is in excellent health.
很好。
Good.
好了各位，我们继续。
A" right, everyone, we are moving on.
我们回到
第一部分第三幕第二场
We're going back to
Part I, Act Three, Scene Two
哈里，请你站到这里来，
舞台左侧，理查德站这里。
Harry, if I could have you here,
upstage left, and Richard here.
哦，王座会放在这里，
舞台右侧前方，
Oh, and the throne will be
down here, downstage right,
头顶会有美妙的白色灯光。
with a marvellous white light from above.
好 开始吧
贵族们刚刚散开。
All right Here we are
The lords have just scattered.
国王，王子...谢谢你，哈里。
The King, the Prince Thank you, Harry.
我不知道是否上帝如此安排
I know not whether God will have it so
因我某些不敬之举，
for some displeasing service
I have done,
但你在人生历程中
but thou dost in thy passages of life
让我深信
make me believe
that thou art only marked
你是上天派来
for the hot vengeance
用炽热复仇之火
惩罚我误入歧途的使者。
and the rod of heaven
to punish my mistreadings.
陛下明鉴，但愿我能
So please Your Majesty, I would I could
"洗清"所有罪过，我。
"quit a" offences, I.
嗯。
Um.
能"洗清"吗？
Could a"?
用如此清白...不 我想起来了。
With as clear - No I have it.
我 我会的。
I I shall.
我会的。
I shall.
我，呃
I, uh
从今往后，我仁慈的君主，
I shall hereafter, my thrice gracious lord,
定当改过自新。
be more myself.
理查德，你跳过了整整一页。
You skipped an entire page
there, Richard.
离演出只剩几天了，
你还没脱稿。
We're a matter of days away,
and you're still not off-book.
是的，我意识到了。
Yes, I am aware of that.
我们再来一次
呃，达芙妮？
We will do that again
Uh, Daphne?
这个人在我的排练室做什么？
Who is this person
in my rehearsal room?
"他跟我一起的，托尼"稍后解释。
"He's with me, Tony I'" explain later.
好了，我们继续吧。
A" right, let's get on with it.
让我们从头再来一遍
Let's pick it up again from the top
哈里，请按你的节奏来
Harry, please, in your own time
理查德。
Richard.
距离我上次来斯特拉特福
已经四年了。
It's been four years
since I was last in Stratford.
我要去圣三一教堂
表达敬意。
I shall go to the Holy Trinity,
pay my respects.
你去过墓地了吗？
You've visited the grave?
还没。
No Not yet.
那么。
So.
你觉得怎么样？
What did you think?
很好。
Good.
是的，呃，有意思。
Yes, uh Interesting.
你想不想——很好
Do you want to - Good
很好。
Good.
那我今天的工作就到此为止。
Then I'm finished for the day.
要来一杯吗？
Care for one?
不，呃，我就不用了，谢谢。
No, uh, not for me, thanks.
要知道，我是个矿工的儿子。
You see, I am the son of a miner.
矿工一到五点就开始喝酒。
At five o'clock, a miner starts drinking.
当然。
Of course.
好吧，我。
Well, I.
"我祝愿你"一切顺利。
"I wish you a" the very best with it.
那就继续吧。
Go on then.
告诉我你的想法。
Te" me your thoughts.
给。
Here.
"老实说，理查德，
我的想法是这样的。
We", candidly, Richard,
my thoughts are these.
首先，你不是矿工，
Firstly, you are not a miner,
你是个演员。
you're an actor.
你是个只有三天时间的演员
You're an actor with three days
来挽救可能是你职业生涯中
最重要的机会。
to salvage what might be
the opportunity of your career.
这个机会能让你在世界
最负盛名的剧院里
The chance to establish yourself
as a classical actor
确立自己作为古典演员的地位。
in the most prestigious theatre
in the world.
你难道不明白这有多重要吗？
Do you not understand
the magnitude of that?
有点——很好。
Somewhat - Good.
那我建议我们找点吃的，然后开始工作。
Then I propose we find some food
and get down to work.
"我了解你"，并将暂时容忍
"I know you a", and will awhile uphold
你那不受约束的懒散幽默"。
the unyoked humour of your idleness".
"但在此我将效仿太阳。"
"Yet herein will I imitate the sun."
再来一次。
Try again.
"我了解你"，
"I know you a",
并将暂时容忍
and will awhile uphold
你那不受约束的懒散幽默"。
the unyoked humour of your idleness".
"但在此我将效仿太阳。"
"Yet herein will I imitate the sun."
你理解这个角色，理查德。
You understand this character, Richard.
你知道他不是那种
拍大腿的轻浮青年。
You know that he's not
some thigh-slapping youth.
是的，哈尔是个年轻人，
Yes, Hal is a young man,
但他始终清楚自己的命运。
but he's always aware of his destiny.
那就是，在他父亲去世后，
That, on the death of his father,
他将不得不告别福斯塔夫
的玩世不恭
he will have to turn away
from Falstaff's irreverence
和酒馆里的醉生梦死。
and the drunken life of the tavern.
他将蜕变为一位国王，
He will transform into a king,
并且，像国王一样，
and, like a king,
以身作则地领导他的国家。
lead his country
as a king must, by example.
你必须相信自己的直觉，理查德。
You must trust your instincts, Richard.
好了，停！停，停！
All right, stop Stop, stop!
我让你喊，你却小声说；
我让你笑，你却——
I tell you to shout, and you
whisper I tell you to laugh
我不是来给你那些搞笑台词
当捧哏的。
I am not some straight man
to your funny lines.
这是场喜剧戏。
It is a comic scene.
我们在酒馆里，这是个粗俗的世界。
We're in the tavern, a world of ribaldry.
听着，你为什么不试试这样做。
Look, why don't you try doing it like.
我绝不会用其他方式演绎
There is no other way I will be doing it
理查德，我才是导演！
Richard, I am your director!
你只能呈现我的表演版本 别人的不行
And you shall have
my performance Nobody else's.
别人的不行？那他在这儿干什么？
Nobody else's? Then what exactly
is he doing here?
托尼 说真的 我觉得你应该接受这个改编
Tony Tony, honestly,
I think you should go with it
虽然与众不同 但效果确实不错
I know it's different,
but I think it is working.
该死的威尔士佬
Bloody Welsh.
你们翻山越岭而来
Over the Marches you come,
out of the mountains,
劫掠我们的牲畜 从不为建设出力
raiding our cattle
You don't come to contribute.
就是群该死的强盗
You're just bloody raiders.
文法学校出身的平民小子
A grammar school boy.
既非王子 也非贵族
Not a prince Not a lord.
三百年过去了
Three hundred years
我们仍为他的文字倾倒
and we're still transported by his words.
明天见 里奇
Tomorrow, Richie.
吹响号角
Sound trumpets.
让我们的战旗飘扬
Let our bloody colours wave.
不成功
And either victory
便成仁
or else a grave.
早啊 里奇
Morning, Rich.
蒂姆
Tim.
你朋友在找你
Your friend's looking for you.
那个...你的表演指导
Your, uh Your acting coach.
他不是我的表演指导
He's not my acting coach.
好吧 那...
Well, then, uh
不管他是谁
you know, whoever he is.
我想讨论下加冕戏
I, uh, thought we might discuss
the coronation scene.
我有六小时演出
I have a six-hour performance.
当然 但...
Of course Of course, but
这场戏结尾有句台词
there's a line towards
the end of the scene
能凸显角色经历的
which underlines
the scale of the transformation
巨大转变
he has undergone.
我需要透口气
I need some air.
伯顿先生？
Mr Burton?
能签个名吗？
Would you mind signing this?
天呐 看看这个
Dear me, look at that.
他们到底在想什么鬼？
"What the he" were they thinking?
谢谢
Thank you
你还在这儿？
Are you still here?
里奇？
Richie?
怎么了？
Yes What is it?
什么意思？
What do you mean?
我等了你将近两小时
I have been waiting for you
for nearly two hours.
等我准备好了自然会来
Yes And I will be along
when I'm good and ready
别忘了是你请我来帮忙的
Richie, I remind you,
I was summoned here to help you.
我也很忙
I, too, am a busy man.
你以为消失八年之后
Do you think you can just turn up
还能随叫随到？
after eight years?
整整八年 还想让我对你言听计从？
Eight bloody years And
and have me do your bidding?
当我还是你学生吗？
Like I'm your schoolboy again?
里奇 这里不方便说话 我们换个地方
Richie I cannot talk here Let's go away.
你他妈以为自己算老几？
Just who the hell do you think you are?
我可是这个该死的国家里
I am one of the most promising
young actors
最有前途的年轻演员之一
in this whole bloody country.
你呢？
And you?
提醒我一下
Remind me.
你又是谁？
Who are you?
哦 里奇
Oh, Richie.
哦 里奇 妈
Oh, Richie - Ma.
见到你真是太高兴了
Oh, it's so wonderful to see you.
我知道
I know.
伯顿先生昨天打电话来了
Mr Burton telephoned yesterday
所以我告诉他
and so I told him
that we'd keep it a surprise.
但他设法给我弄了张票
But he's managed to get me a ticket.
哦 里奇 你一定很自豪吧
Oh, Richie, you must be so proud.
他说能弄到一张票
He said it was all he could do
just to get the one,
毕竟你们俩都在参与这部戏
what with both of you
working on the play, so.
是啊
Yes.
这地方是不是很棒？
Isn't this a wonderful place?
伯顿先生跟我讲过很多这里的事
Mr Burton has told me so much about it
真不敢相信我真的来了
I can't believe I'm really here.
哦 里奇
Oh, Richie.
若终年皆是游乐假期
If all the year
were playing holidays
嬉戏将如劳作般令人厌倦
to sport would be as tedious as to work.
当我摒弃这放浪形骸
So when this loose behaviour I throw off,
偿还从未许诺的债务
and pay the debt I never promised
我的行动将比誓言更为珍贵
By how much better than my word I am
对不起
I'm sorry.
真的很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
我说的话不可原谅
It's unforgivable what I said.
不可原谅 而且完全不是事实
Unforgivable and entirely untrue.
我当时喝醉了
I was drunk.
又喝醉了
Again.
这不能成为借口
It was no excuse.
我欠你的
I owe you
太多太多
everything.
我从未对你说过
I've never said it to you
我甚至从未
I've never even
道过歉 所以
apologised So.
所以现在我要感谢你 也要向你道歉
So, I thank you and I apologise now.
真心实意地
Truly, with all my heart.
我害怕
I'm afraid.
我真的害怕
I am I'm afraid.
我不像你
I'm not like you.
我就是个该死的冒牌货
I'm just a bloody fake.
顶多算半个演员
I'm half an actor.
我善妒 傲慢 自私又刻薄
And I'm jealous and proud
and selfish and spiteful.
而你拥有一切
And you are everything.
你很坚强 真的
You're strong Truly, you are.
这部戏 PH
And this play, PH
这就是我们为之奋斗的一切。
this is everything we worked for.
而我却感到恐惧。
And I'm terrified.
我害怕极了。
I'm terrified.
求你了。
Please.
帮帮我。
Help me.
回来吧
Come back
我必须走了
I have to go
现在，哈尔，
现在是什么时辰了，小子？
Now, Hal,
what time of day is it, lad?
汝
Thou
因痛饮陈年美酒而愚钝至此
art so fat-witted with drinking of old sack
竟忘却追问那真正
that thou hast forgotten
to demand that truly
汝心所向之事。
which thou wouldst truly know.
时辰与你何干？
What a devil hast thou to do
with the time of day?
除非时光化作美酒盏盏，
分秒变为肥鸡只只，
Unless hours were cups of sack,
and minutes capons,
而钟表是老鸨的巧舌如簧
and clocks the tongues of bawds
切莫如此作想；事实绝非这般。
Do not think so; You shall not find it so.
愿上帝宽恕那些
And God forgive them
that so much have swayed.
使陛下对我
Your Majesty's good thoughts
away from me.
我要告诉您：我是您的儿子。
To tell you that I am your son.
为何王冠搁置于
Why doth the crown lie there
upon his pillow,
他那令人不安的枕畔？
being so troublesome a bedfellow?
啊，精雕细琢的烦忧。
Oh, polished perturbation.
黄金般的忧虑
Golden care
令睡梦之门
that keep'st the ports
of slumber open wide
向无数不眠之夜敞开
to many a watchful night.
吾王，我的朱庇特，
我向您倾诉衷肠。
My King, my Jove,
I speak to thee, my heart.
我不认得你，老翁。
I know thee not, old man.
快去做你的祷告吧。
Fa" to thy prayers.
白发配愚人是何等荒唐。
How ill white hairs
become a fool and a jester.
我长久以来梦见这般人物。
I have long dreamt of such a kind of man.
但醒来后，
But being awaked,
我对梦境嗤之以鼻
I do despise my dream
太棒了！
Bravo!
精彩绝伦，谢谢
Wonderful, thank you
当然
Of course
里奇。
Richie.
第五幕，第五场。
Act Five, Scene Five.
你的声音转换真是。
The modulation of your voice It was.
你的静默表现确实。
Well, your stillness, it was really.
呃，我真的。
Uh, I was really.
我，呃，从未。
Well, I, uh, I have never.
什么？
What?
难道儿子不能拥抱
自己的亲生父亲吗？
Can a man not hug
his own bloody father?
-